Sweet and Lowdown is a comedy, drama, music film directed by Woody Allen.
In the 1930s, jazz guitarist Emmet Ray idolizes Django Reinhardt,
faces gangsters and falls in love with a mute woman.
Emmet Ray, played by Sean Penn.
Hattie, played by Samantha Morton.
Al Torrio, played by Anthony LaPaglia.
Blanche Williams, played by Uma Thurman.
Harry, played by James Urbaniak.
Mr. Haynes, played by John Waters.
Sweet and Lowdown is a 1999 American comedy-drama
mockumentary written and directed by Woody Allen.
Loosely based on Federico Fellini's film La Strada, the film tells the story of jazz guitarist Emmet Ray
(played by Sean Penn) who falls in love with mute laundress Hattie (Samantha Morton).
Like several of Allen's other films (e.g., Zelig), the film is occasionally interrupted by interviews with critics and biographers like Allen,
Nat Hentoff, Daniel Okrent, and Douglas McGrath, who comment on the film's plot as if the characters were real-life people.
The film received generally positive reviews upon release, with Penn and Morton receiving
Oscar nominations for Best Actor and Best Supporting Actress, respectively.
The film explores themes of new york city, jazz,
guitar, night life, egocentrism.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.